It's easy to imagine that after Saturday
night, the game was up. Shannan had
busted Watts and there was going to be
hell to pay when she got back. But if
you if you thought that, you'd be wrong.
Remember, Shannan's pregnant. No matter
what's going on with her husband, she
absolutely has to find a way to make it
work. Unfortunately, Watts feels exactly
the same way about Kessinger. He
absolutely has to find a way to make
that work to keep things going with her.
And so what we have here just one day
before the murders is an inevitable
conflict brewing. Can you see what's
going on here is inevitable. This has
been going on for a long time. Now it's
coming to a head. Now the good news is
Shannan is starting to think critically.
You know her checking on that restaurant
bill is thinking critically. The bad
news is just as she starts to suspect
him, she second-guesses herself. If she
had somehow kept trying to figure things
out that day with one day to go, who
knows? Perhaps she could have somehow
saved herself. Don't laugh. Don't scoff.
I mean, it might seem silly, but even
the fates seem to be trying to talk to
her that day. in Phoenix that day there
was a big storm so big that the lights
went out that power went out in the
restaurant and if I remember correctly
their flight was delayed other flights
from Thrivers were actually cancelled
and they had to rescheduled their
flight. It was if the as if the fates
didn't want Shannan to get on a plane
and so had they returned with everyone
else had they rescheduled the flight to
the next day may well have missed his
window and these crimes may never have
happened. Another way of thinking about
it is the fact that Shannan was supposed
to arrive at 11:00 at night but instead
arrived at 2:00 in the morning because
he had just had a 111 minute
conversation with Kessinger because he
was sleepd deprived because he was still
in a way triggered by Kessinger and
because he was fearful that Shannan
would find out perhaps because of all of
that he acted basically in a rash way
very early that morning and the family
annihilation
started actually with Shenan. I got
nightmares in my head. I feel
my mind feels like a creature
haunts me so much.
I got my
Hello and welcome to True Crime Rocket
Science, the most authentic voice in
true crime. Well, we finally come to the
last day. It's Shannan's last full day
on Earth and Bella and Cece's as well.
Ironically, none of them are going to be
home. Shannan is thriving in Arizona and
her kids are at a birthday party where
they aren't allowed to eat cake, you
know, just in case there are nuts in it.
And they are not terribly happy about
that. According to the discovery, Chris
and the girls Bella and Celeste were at
the Lindstöm's residence on Sunday the
12th for their son Caden's birthday
party. Chris was described as acting
normal at the birthday party. That is a
quiet person and doesn't show emotion
much. The Lindstöm said that he was
watching after the girls. They said that
there were five or six adults and five
or six kids at the party. Now, to them,
they thought Chris was acting normal,
but actually he wasn't acting completely
normal, and we'll see why in a second.
But before we get to that, if you
haven't subscribed to the channel,
please do. If you are familiar with all
my videos on this case, you might want
to try reading the books, which provide
a much more comprehensive and consistent
narrative with far more insights than
these videos. You might want to have a
look at the link that I've provided in
the description. Also, for those who
watch until the end of the outro, I do
try try to change the outro with scenes
from travels all over the United States,
all over Europe as well, France,
Portugal. Bear in mind, I investigated
crimes in Orve, as well as I've also
visited Tenneref. So, you might want to
stay tuned because we do try and change
the outro for every video. If you've
enjoyed this 21 episode series so far
and you've never hit the thanks button
and you want to show your appreciation,
now's your chance and let's get started.
So, one can imagine what's at this
birthday party seeing a lot of kids
running around, you know, having his own
childhood perhaps awakened and his own
love for children triggered. This is yet
another scenario that might just soften
his heart. the laughter of children, the
spectacle of children having fun. But
will it? And if it doesn't, why doesn't
it? Well, we'll attempt to answer that
question in this analysis. Now, let's
drill down into the events of August
12th, that final day. Starting at 0732,
not found in Watts's phone, Shannan sent
him a message. Good morning, baby. Love
you. 0758. Shannan told Eddie, "I got a
lot of work to do today and this week.
Next weekend I'm going to go MIA while
away with Chris in Aspen. Think about
those words. I'm going to go MIA.
0809 hours. Shannan asked how the girls
were. What said that they were good and
drinking a shake. Shannan replied, "Miss
you guys, give them kisses for me." Watt
said he would. And Shannan told him to
have a great day. He reciprocated. 0811.
Josh asked Watts if he was truly all
right with Josh and his family staying
with the Watts family when they moved.
That's when the Rosenbergs moved. You
know, they were going to move via the
Watts home. Watts said, "That's cool,
man." Watts went on to describe the
finish of the Rockies game. It was epic.
0835. Shannan told Addie, "I need to do
better with my calendar. I don't block
out family time. I fill in family time."
He meaning Chris Chris Watt said to me
last night it has nothing to do with the
business though. Eddie said that she
thought that this could have been the
issue and insisted Shannan make more
time for the family. Shannan replied,
"No, I agree." No, I think it's itty
bitty things. I sometimes can be [__]
and he gets that side of me. I know I
tend to make him feel like he isn't able
to do things because I have control
issues. He said the other night that he
wishes I just let him hang up a picture.
So there Shannan herself is saying I
have control issues. Thinking globally,
do you think this is really what Chris
Watts wanted wants that that he wants
more Shannan to make more family time
with him? Anyway, 0900 hours Shannan's
calendar had entry titled talk scheduled
for a particular time and date. Now it's
unclear whether Chris Watts would have
seen that entry as well. If it did, it
probably would have given him chills.
Now, is Shannan right when she says it's
itty bitty things that are the problem
in their relationship? I think she's
right in a general sense, but not right
here. Not right here on her last day. I
think itty bitty things eventually
become being severely financially
stressed, for example. That's not itty
bitty. You know, it's interesting that
Watts apparently said to her it has
nothing to do with the business. I think
that's because he wanted her to go to
Arizona. I think he in his heart of
hearts believes that it had a lot to do
with the business. What do you think?
Did he approve of her making money as an
MLM or not? Then she says, "Sometimes I
can be a bit [__] You can see that
Shenan is doing some self-reflection and
even being a little self-critical in the
final hours of her life." Now, many
people following this case have given me
a lot of grief for the slightest comment
about Shannan that isn't positive. So, I
wonder whether they're going to
criticize Shannan now for criticizing
herself. Is she the victim victim
blaming herself now as well? In other
words, is it always wrong just to try
and be a little aware of how one can
improve in how one is doing certain
things? Is is it something you should
never ever do? And on August 12th,
Shannan is just getting started.
According to the phone data review, at
9:04, Shannan continues with Eddie. She
says, "I always have, but he also never
calls me out. He never fights me. He
just goes with the flow. He and I know I
like things done a certain way, but I
never thought about how that makes him
feel as a man. I don't even know if this
is what's bothering him." He still
hasn't said. I'm praying he wrote me a
letter like I like like I asked since he
can express himself better in a letter
than talking. Well, we know that Chris
didn't write a letter back. Shannan
added, "I'm the pusher and he's the
withdrawer. He has strengths that are my
weaknesses and vice versa." Shannan
continued, "The lack of communication
isn't on my part. I can be better at how
I communicate, but he doesn't
communicate. I say things sometimes just
to get him to react in any way." Think
about those words. I say things
sometimes just to get a reaction since
he doesn't react and that's not good.
It's not even all the time. 99% of the
time we are perfectly fine and we have
never ever fought literally over
anything serious.
Is that true at this point in time that
they've never fought over anything
serious? Right now they fighting over
whether he wants a baby, whether they
should stay married, whether they should
sell the house. Then she says, "I fought
with him over stupid [__] like not doing
something I asked in a timely manner."
Shannan said, "I did belittle him
without realizing it with his parents. I
told him he needed to find his balls and
protect his family." Shannan said that
watch is submissive when his family are
involved. And he said that this is Wat's
disposition and added pretty ominously,
he would kill for you. Well, the reality
is he would kill for Kessinger. He is
about to kill for Kessinger. And by that
I don't mean Kessinger asked him to
kill. I mean he in his heart is killing
so that he can make this relationship
with Kessinger possible in his mind. We
also know that from what's told the
investigators, he said being around
Shannan was like always walking on
eggshells. That was his version of this
whole story, his version of events. And
let me ask you, do you think that was
true? And do you think he felt like he
was walking on eggshells with Kissinger?
Shannan told Eddie, "I told him in a
letter I would fight for him and there
has to be mutual respect. I did respect
his parents enough to deal with them.
His mom just didn't and went alone with
me jabs at me. It's not fair. I mean,
[__] I agree to spend 5 weeks with both
parents. That's hell for me. But I did
it for him and the kids." Shannan
continued, "He was never close to anyone
but his dad. I being the family person
tried bringing them closer and it
backfired. I need to feel like he will
stand up for us faced with difficult
situations. That's where he flaws.
That's his weakness. Shannan told Eddie,
"My weakness is I have an Italian temper
that can't hold back when pissed. I'm a
fixer and I want to talk this out." And
he just wants to work it out in his
head. I've just been acting kind of
normal. Morning baby. Love you, etc. But
not overdoing it. Overdoing it is what
we do. We are so affectionate but can't
stop touching each other. It's not just
the sex, just the touch. At 0957,
Shannan asked, "Watt, can you do me a
favor today? If you have time, can you
get the backpacks ready for tomorrow
with blankies and spare clothes, please?
If not, I can do it in the A.M." Watt
said that he would. And so it is very
surprising to me and it warms my heart
that you're the type of dad who can pack
a bag in the morning and you know you
just what to put in there and you know
just what to put in there as a backup in
case they have an accident. Okay? You
know what the clothes to put in there.
You know what they have for breakfast.
You know what they have for a snack and
a dinner and a nighttime snack. You can
tell me the book you read to your
daughters. Okay. I know you love them.
And you're not faking that are you? It's
real. Okay, there's a lot of guys who
come in here and try to tell me that and
I know they're lying, okay? Cuz they
can't answer those questions that you
can answer, okay?
But you're here today lying about
something else.
So, we need to talk about that, okay?
About your daughter. I know
>> this is a brilliant move by Koda because
he was basically going into an area that
was very true that showed that he really
did understand Chris Watts. And this
came out in this last day of the phone
data review. Obviously Koda read it,
read some of what was going on or else
was otherwise informed. And so he was
aware of this aspect to Chris Watts that
made Chris Watts think that he was he
was completely an open book to the
investigator. And it was when he did
this that Chris Watts actually broke for
the first time when he was interrogated.
and it was a big step confessing that he
cheated to Shannan. This was the first
person that I think he'd effectively
told that he was having an affair with
besides possibly his father. Now I do
think Shannan sort of getting the input
of her friends like Eddie you know
putting your heads together and trying
to resolve a situation although I think
that is good sometimes in or when you
have ordinary problems there are certain
crises that you go through that other
people simply can't know the full extent
of only you do and that's where you you
really do have to think for yourself
only you know your true situation only
you know your intuitions. Only you know
all of those subtleties. And sometimes
only you can make the hard right
decision. And so where Shannan says, "My
weakness is that I have an Italian
temper." Aren't we allowed to talk about
Shannan's weaknesses? And doesn't that
mean Shannan isn't allowed to either?
And so by the same token, if we can go
into this area in a criminal case, maybe
we can go into the same area in our own
lives, deal with our own weaknesses,
address our own shortcomings. So the
point is when we examine the timeline,
we we the living ought to be allowed to
think critically. Thinking critically
doesn't mean criticizing. It means
evaluating what we know and finding
better solutions, better answers than
the people in this story. God knows we
they could have come to a better result,
a better answer to the problem that they
were facing than Chris Watts in prison,
Kishinger's life ruined and Shannan, the
baby, the girls all dead. Surely there's
a better answer than that. And I would
hazard if you ask them directly, if you
ask Shannan, ask Chris Watts if this was
an exercise worth doing in your life,
like really exploring the alternatives
in, in other words, to the worst
alternative. I think they would say
absolutely.
And so, personally, I think it's
fantastic that Shannan was doing sincere
introspection about how she could do
certain things better. All of us should
do this. It's unfortunate that Chris
Watts wasn't doing the same thing that
day. And ironically, Kessinger sort of
was. That day, she said to her friend
Charlotte Nelson that she thought he
seemed a little too good to be true.
Well, she was right. Let's have a look
at those texts. And so, bear in mind,
these texts are being exchanged while
Chris Watts is sort of preoccupied at
the party. Charlotte Nelson, Nicole
Kessing's best friend, texts her at
13:45 hours on the 12th. How old is he?
Nicole answers 33, I think. Nicole, I
just feel like I will always be second
place. Like, he's been there, done that.
It's early though. We will see. He's
very kind to me. And he works out, so
he's super sexy. Don't tell nobody. I
haven't made up my mind on him yet.
Like, he seems too good to be true.
Later that afternoon at 11 minutes to 3,
she says, "Haha, yeah, it's the best sex
I've ever had. I'm hooked. And then I
think he really likes me. So in
Kissinger's case, it seems like the sex
has clouded her ability to think
critically. And for Chris Watts, perhaps
even more so. Let's go back to the
timeline. 10:32. Shannan asked Watts to
send some pictures of the girls. I miss
them. Roughly 18 hours before their
murders, Watts took one of the last
known images of Celeste in life. He sent
this and one of Bella taken at the same
time to Shannan. Then 10:45 hours watch
searched Google for Mount K lima. He
preserved an image of the volcano
spewing lava and smoke. So what is he
doing between feeding the kids while
he's having kind of online conversations
texts with Kessinger? And do you think
that's going to continue while he's at
the birthday party? Where is this moment
to re-evaluate life including the the
lives the value of the lives just how
precious these children are to him? At
11:13 hours, Shannan asked if the girls
were taking a nap. Watt said that they
were just laying down. Shannan asked
Watts, "If you have time before they
wake up and want to call me back, I'd
love to talk to you." Well, what said
okay. Guess what? He never did. 1217.
Perhaps the last image of Shannan taken
in life. They met today confirmed the
date and time. Ultimately, the last
image we have of Shannan is actually of
her um via the doorbell camera, but
we'll get to that. I do think there's a
more recent photo of Shannan at the
Thrive uh dinner that's more recent than
this one. 13:30 hours watch took
photographs of the girls playing in the
distance in a backyard near a small
pool. That was at the Lindstöm's
birthday party.
But of course, his focus isn't actually
on them. Although he seems normal to the
people around him, when he's looking at
his phone, they're probably assuming
he's texting Shannan. But, you know,
just like he was at the trampoline park
in Myrtle Beach, he's distracted. He's
stealing the odd text with Kessinger.
And if anything, it's a bummer. It's a
drain on him to be here with them rather
than where he he's absolutely yearning
to be with her. According to the
discovery, we are aware that there was
some drama at the birthday party.
Towards the end of the party, Celeste
fell in a swing set in the backyard and
Chris had to comfort her and Celeste
said that she wanted her blanket. Jeremy
and Jennifer said that Chris has always
been good with the girls. They described
him as a mellow guy. And so perhaps
that's where he decides that he wants
them out of the picture as well at this
birthday party. The babysitting thing is
just too much work, too expensive. I'm
talking about hiring a babysitter and
takes too much time, you know, when he's
got to look after them. The Google
search at 10:45 for Mount Kyma was also
obviously related to Kale Lima. We see
more of this as the day continued.
What's thinking about her? He also
Googles Dead Sea Scrolls. Watson
Kessinger also exchanged text at the
birthday party while he's there. That's
another aspect covered in detail in the
narratives. Let's look at some of those
texts. 8:12, that's the 12th of August.
At 3:14 p.m., that would be slappbang in
the middle of the birthday party. He
writes, "Nice. That sounds like a good
time. I haven't seen an IMAX in a
while." So, she's talking about taking
him to a movie. Sounds like you're
having a fun day with the folks. I'm
still at the birthday party. Kids are
soaked from water balloons. Then, almost
an hour later, he texts her bean
pounding fruit and had a whole jar of
asparagus. He didn't smoke any barbecue
this time. He did hot dogs, so I did the
fruit and veggies. At some point early
in the day, Kessinger texted him, "No,
you can't buy the scrolls. Do the Dead
Sea Scrolls are some of the oldest, most
important writing in the world." At
1446, we see another message from Ronny
Watts in the phone data review, the
second in two consecutive days. But what
about their correspondence before that?
At 1656, Watch is still trying to sound
like he knows something about geology to
his new girlfriend. Again, this is where
his head's at. At 1556 hours, Shannan
asked if the girls had fun at the party.
Watts said that they were still there
and they were having fun. Shannan
replied, "Good. I'm glad. Okay, love
you." Watts did not respond. 1844 hours,
a photo was created in his image file
documenting the temperature setting in
the refrigerator. 1847 hours. A photo of
four chicken breasts on a barbecue grill
was created in his image file. 1706
Watch told Cody Roberts his coworker, "I
have the whip checks for the service
629. I'm going to go straight out there
from my house in the morning. I will
look at the 319 as well and run the 1129
if you want." So there we have absolute
confirmation that at 17:06 at 6 minutes
past 5, watches not only decided to
murder his family, but where he's going
to put their bodies. In other words,
this happens immediately after he comes
back from the birthday party. So in a
way, it's almost as if the birthday
party is where he's thinking about
murder. the practicalities of it. You
know, where is he going? What he's going
to do with their bodies? And he's
thinking about this because the clock is
ticking. As far as he knows, Shannan is
going to be home in six hours. And so,
at the very last moment, he's starting
to plan the murder. And bear in mind, he
chooses the well site more for the kids
than for Shannan because Shenan he
buries in the sand. The kids are put
into the oil tanks. And so, he's
literally already decided that part as
well. Now, if Cody Roberts had replied,
"I'm going to do it. Don't worry about
it." Uh, it's another possibility that
this crime may not have been able to
take place. But instead, at 17:20,
Roberts replies, "I was going to head
out there first thing tomorrow to check
out the 319. Did Troy talk to you about
what I had found there Friday
afternoon?" So, basically here, he's
saying, you know, I I'm going to
actually do it at 1723 hours. At 3
minutes later, what's answered? Yep. I
was standing right next to him. I was
giving him a fire stick to look at. I
can go out there though. No sense in
both of us going out there. Lol. 1726
hours. Watch search Google for the Dead
Sea Scroll. So again, in between really
planning the nuts and bolts of this
murder, he's in he's basically thinking
about how to talk to Kessinger and how
to respond to some of her questions and
comments. 1809 hours and that's really
when it's carved in in stone really.
Roberts responded, "All right, sounds
good, man. I appreciate it." Mean
meaning you can go out to 319 by
yourself that morning first thing in the
morning. And guess what he's going to do
when he does that? He's going to hide
the disposal of his children of his
family in this just going to the work
site. And in a sense, he succeeded
because no one could imagine or believe
what he had actually done. As far as the
investigators were concerned, for a good
long while, the family had simply
disappeared. Cody Roberts goes on to
say, "I can let you know in the morning
and let me know if you find anything at
the 319. If we if not, we may pressure
test that BP line and see if it's
leaking underground." 1946 hours.
Shannan asked, "Hey honey, kids in bed?"
and asked for pictures. Watch replied,
"Bella just back in bed." Shannan noted,
"They must be exhausted." Ominously,
Watch resent the images from early in
the day at the dinner table. And then he
added this image taken late in the day
at the birthday party, the last known
image of Bella in life. And I must say
when I first saw that I thought at this
point I'm sure that the girls aren't
alive anymore especially because he
ended up having this 111minute
conversation with with Kessinger and he
probably didn't want to be overheard by
his own children. In any event, now the
fates are really working. It's 1954
hours Shenant's watch. The power went
out during dinner with Cindy and Addie
before uh the airport and then she sent
a photograph of the darkened restaurant.
She commented on the photograph just
sent. Great job on Bella's hair. And
watch replied, "That sucks." "Yeah," she
cooperated. Shannan explained, "Really
bad dust storm, rain, thunder, and
lightning." Shannan said that Cindy
bought their dinner. Shannan concluded,
"Praying it doesn't cancel flight.
Eddie's flight was canled this morning."
2020 20 hours. Shannan called Watts and
held a 9-minute conversation, revealing
how their talk went. Immediately after
the call, she told Watts, "Sorry I
bothered you. I just wanted to talk to
you." Well, Watts has really done. He's
at the point where he's about to commit
these murders. He's he's decided to do
it. And what he really wants to do at
this point is talk to Kessinger. He's
also frustrated that he can't be
spending the night with her. 2031,
Shannan told Eddie that she can call
Chris about Jack. He's up. And so at
2033, Shenanfeld watched, "Thank you for
taking good care of the kids this
weekend so I can learn and work. I
appreciate it." 20 45 hours. Watts
returned a missed call to Eddie and held
a 16-minute conversation. Moments later,
he told Shannan, "You're welcome. I just
talked to Addie." In their follow-up
messages, it's clear that Watts offered
Eddie mechanical advice on a car. So,
this is what he's doing on a Sunday
night. And you know, instead of him
talking to Shannan, he's talking to
Eddie. Eddie's very aware of what's
going on. And so, one does wonder
whether that was manufactured as well
where Shannan is trying to get Edd's
impression of Watts and whether she can
pick up anything that's going on. 219
hours Shannan asked Watts, "What kind of
vegetables do you want with dinner
tomorrow?" Watts replied, "Green beans."
Shannan said that she would buy them
tomorrow at Costco along with other
items. Of course, that would not happen
because this was her last today. There
would be no tomorrow. Shannan soon told
Watts that she was ready to come home.
I'm ready for bed. 21 11 hours. Shannan
sent a message to Addie explaining the
accompanying text that was what what
Shannan planned to till watch tomorrow
night. The message read, "Can you please
tell me something? Because just like
you, I'm in my head." So, you can tell
that Shannan is very aware that
something's going on. I try to fix thing
and make make them better and this is
making me crazy. I know that you need
time. I want to give you what you're
asking for and respect your space. I
need some time. This place that I'm in
in my head is not a good place. Well, it
certainly wasn't. It is not healthy for
me or Nikico. I need you to help me or
help me help you. I need you to give me
just a little bit of what I did or
didn't do so that I'm not going crazy in
my head or figure it out. So she's
saying, "Please tell me what I did wrong
or what I didn't do. I know I can't fix
this by myself that we are going to have
to work together." So again, here she's
thinking critically at the very last
moment that night. You know, let's sort
out this problem, but you know, it's too
late. He's already decided to murder
them. 2129 hours. Shannan made an
unanswered call to Watts. 2144.
Why do you think that that was an
unanswered call? 2144 Shannan told Watts
tried calling you to give you an update
was starting to board and they announced
that our crew isn't here yet and it's
going to be a minimum of an hour before
they are here. And so at at this time
Watts understood that Shannan would be
on the flight which meant the coast was
clear for him to call Kessinger. And so
even though she isn't on that flight,
Watts isn't going to put Watts isn't
going to end the call with Kessinger. He
really wants to be with her physically
with her in bed at her home. The best
that he can get is 111 minute
conversation.
2145 hours Shannan receives a calendar
alert. Flight 6149 from Phoenix to
Denver. 23 21 hours. Watts finally
replies. Why? because he's had this
conversation with Kessinger. And I think
it's really interesting that it's not
included in the phone data review. One
actually has the idea either that this
was an error made by the compilers of
the phone data review or that they
purposefully left it out in order to
protect Kessinger from a from
accusations and fingers pointing her
way. Right. It seems like they
deliberately left it out. Anyway, Watts
finally replied, "Holy crap. Sorry I
passed out on the couch. that's going to
be late. And I think the terms he used
there, he leaves on his phone. He knows
that that's going to be that's going to
be recorded. And so it sounds very
conversational, very familiar, but
otherwise he's ignored. Shannan, so if
we take the phone data review at face
value and we don't think critically
about it, it's a little anomaly for
which there might be a few explanations.
The fact that Watts takes 90 minutes to
respond to a text. Perhaps he did pass
on pass out on the couch. Is that right?
Did he pass out on the couch like he
said? Actually, no. Missing from the
phone data review are Kessinger's calls,
including arguably the most material
phone call of the entire case. This one
lasting 111 minutes at 2121. Bear in
mind what's calling, not the other way
around. Well, that brings us to the end
of August 12th. And you can see just how
important the phone data review is going
all the way back to July, even before
that, June as well. And I hope while
we've done this review, you've realized
the significance of context and how it
plays out into motive and the execution
of a crime. Thank you very much for
listening to this series. Take care and
I'll see you guys next time.
Heat. Heat. N.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.